<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The right method for the proving of infant-baptism. With some reflections on some late tracts against infant-baptism. / By Joseph Whiston, Minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Whiston, Joseph, d. 1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96326</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201364</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077767</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077767</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151884</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96326)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151884)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2280:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The right method for the proving of infant-baptism. With some reflections on some late tracts against infant-baptism. / By Joseph Whiston, Minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Whiston, Joseph, d. 1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 3-72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson, at the Golden-Lion in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXC. [1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 72.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Infant baptism.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151884:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Right Method For the proving of INFANT-BAPTISM.</p>
            <p>With ſome REFLECTIONS On ſome late <hi>Tracts</hi> againſt INFANT-BAPTISM.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOSEPH WHISTON,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi rend="blackletterType">Ionathan Robinſon,</hi> at the Golden-Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:151884:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151884:2"/>
            <head>The Right Method for the proving of <hi>INFANT-BAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISM,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THAT <hi>Sacred Adagy</hi> delivered to us by the Wiſe Man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.14. is ſadly verified, not only in Temporal, but in Religious Contentions. Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons once begun, be the Object or Subject Matter what it will, are ſeldom ſoon compoſed or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, but often grow to greater Violence, and in reſpect of thoſe that are religious, unſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, unleſs by the interpoſal of a Divine Hand. One Reaſon whereof is, becauſe the Parties li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigant, act under the Inforcement of Conſcience, either regularly, guided by Divine Light, or miſguided by ſome Miſtake the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lies under. 'Tis the unqueſtionable Duty of all Chriſtians, eſpecially the Miniſters of the Goſpel, who are Chriſt's Stewards, intruſted with the Preſervation as well as Diſpenſation of his Truth to the World, to contend for it as well as preach it, ſee <hi>Jude</hi> 3. Now the litigant Parties on both Hands ſuppoſe, at leaſt pretend, they are his Truths they contend for. Neither are all Contentions of this Kind abſolutely reproveable; the Sin uſually is rather in the manner of Management, than in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151884:3"/>Contentions themſelves, as abſolutely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. All Truths (as muſt be granted on all Hands) are not revealed ſo evidently in the Scriptures, as to admit of no Debate about them. Now till Men diſcern what is Truth, it may be uſeful, yea a Duty, to contend for what at preſent they apprehend to be ſo. Yet this muſt be ſaid, that it is Matter of much Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as well as great Lamentation, that after a long ventilation of diſputable Doctrines and Practices, all ſincere and intelligent Chriſtians, who have received any meaſure of that Unction from the Holy One, whereby the Laws of God are put into their Minds, and written in their Hearts; that is, an inward Principle and Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is wrought in them, inclining them to a ready compliance with, and ſubmiſſion to the whole revealed Will of God, ſhould not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern on which ſide Truth lies, ſo as to coaleſce in the ſame Judgment and Practice. Shall we impute it to an Obſcurity in Divine Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? That would be a Reflection upon the Knowledg, Wiſdom, or Faithfulneſs of our Lord Chriſt, <hi>in whom,</hi> as the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>are hid all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledg;</hi> and who, as the ſame Apoſtle aſſures us, <hi>hath been faithful in all his Houſe;</hi> the Fault there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt lie on the part of Chriſtians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. For inſtance, That the Doctrine and Practice of Infant-Baptiſm have been of a long time controverted in the Church, is known to all. Now whence it ſhould be that this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy is not come to an Iſſue, conſidering what hath been ſaid on the one and the other Part,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151884:3"/>but freſh Contentions ſhould ariſe, may juſtly require the moſt ſedate and ſerious Enquiry; but I ſhall not at preſent enlarge upon it. Two things I would only ſay;</p>
            <p>Firſt, That on the Part of thoſe that have pleaded the Cauſe of Paedobaptiſm, I cannot but conclude, that many Miſtakes they have lain under, both about the Tenour of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, on which they have duly founded their pleas, and about the Benefits accruing to Infants by their Covenant, Intereſt, and Baptiſm, did at the firſt in a great meaſure give Riſe to this Controverſy, and have contributed not a little to the long continuance of it. Had the true Tenour of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant been clearly diſcovered, aſſerted and eſtabliſhed by Scripture-Light, and the full Good and Benefit accruing to Infants from their Intereſt therein, and their Baptiſm, as the preſent Token of it, allowed to them in a conſiſtency with all the Truths of the Goſpel, I cannot but think that this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy had been, if not wholly obviated, yet quickly ſuppreſſed among all ſincere and intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Chriſtians. To me 'tis paſt doubt that Miſtakes on the part of Paedobaptiſts, have greatly promoted the Cauſe of Antipaedobap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm: this ſufficiently appears by ſome late Tracts by the Men of that Perſwaſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, On the part of the Antipaedobap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, I ſhall only ſay, that I do heartily wiſh, that if the Lord had ſeen it meet, there had been a more equal Dividend, that thoſe among them that are men of greater Parts and Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, had a greater ſhare with their Brethren of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151884:4"/>lower Parts and Abilities, in their Sincerity, Simplicity, and Love unto Truth, and thoſe weaker Ones had a greater ſhare with their Brethren in thoſe Parts and Abilities they have attained to. Some ſeem ſufficiently furniſhed with Abilities for the finding out, at leaſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Truth when ſet before them, and yet by one Means or another comply not with it, but on the other hand do oppoſe it: Others have ſufficient Sincerity and Love to Truth, to ingage them to a compliance with it when diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, but have not ſuch acuteneſs of Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, nor ſolidity of Judgment, as is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the finding out or diſcerning a Truth that lies at all below the very Surface of the Scriptures. I ſhall therefore, that I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this Controverſy into as narrow a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, and thereby lay the whole of it within the view of the ſhorteſt and narroweſt-ſighted, as poſſibly I may; and alſo obviate all unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Digladiations or Impertinences on the one Hand or the other, preſent, as it were, in a ſhort Scheme, the Method I have proceeded in, in the Pleas I have made on behalf of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-Intereſt and Baptiſm of the Infant-Seed of Believers, and in which I judg it abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary, that whoever will ſucceſsfully plead the ſame Cauſe, do proceed. And thus in the general I have laid the Foundation to the Pleas I have made in that Covenant entered with <hi>Abraham,</hi> recorded in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. For though there be much in the New Teſtament ſtrongly perſwading that it is the Mind and Will of our Lord Chriſt, that the Infant-Seed of his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151884:4"/>People ſhould be by Baptiſm ſolemnly dedicated to him, as joint Confederates with their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, yet it muſt be granted that his Mind and Will is not ſo fully and clearly revealed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as to admit of no Debates about it. Will we have full Satisfaction about the Mind and Will of our Lord Chriſt, with reference to this Practice, we muſt enter at the Revelations he hath made thereof, in the firſt eſtabliſhment of that Covenant with <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet let me add, that I ſuppoſe there is a Miſtake in the Recommenders of a late Tract, paſſing under the Name of Mr. <hi>Philip Cary</hi> to the World, when they ſay that ſome of the Paedobaptiſts themſelves do confeſs, that Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments taken from the Baptizing of whole Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, from Chriſt's bleſſing little Children, and from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. have no weight in them. I remember not that any have confeſſed ſo much, I am ſure they had no Reaſon ſo to do. We only ſay, that thoſe and the like Scriptures, as taken abſtractly by themſelves, do not make ſuch a full, clear, and convincing diſcovery of the Mind of our Lord Chriſt in this. Matter, as to ſet this Practice above all rational Doubts. There is undoubtedly much, yea very much Weight in them, eſpecially when added as a farther Confirmation of what is pleaded from this Covenant: and let any Baptiſts pretend what they will, they never have, nor will be able to anſwer ſome of thoſe Arguments Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath urged from that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. But this I was ſaying in order to a full Eſtabliſhment of this Practice, 'tis abſolutely neceſſary that a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151884:5"/>Foundation be laid where I have laid it, <hi>viz.</hi> in the fore-mentioned Covenant. But more particularly that this Foundation may be ſurely laid, as I have done, ſo all others ingaging in the ſame Cauſe, muſt do theſe five things.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) It muſt be ſolidly proved, that this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is not the Old Covenant which the Apoſtle tells is done away, but that it is the Covenant of Grace, that very Covenant under which Believers ſtill are. And I fear not falling under the Cenſure of over-Confidence in the Minds or Judgments of judicious and unbiaſſed Perſons, if I ſay this is fully done already. See among others my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Cox,</hi> p. 95, to the 139. with the places there referred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, where I have demonſtrated theſe three Poſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God in thoſe Tranſactions with <hi>Abraham,</hi> recorded <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. at the beginning, did not make or eſtabliſh the Covenant of Grace with him: My meaning is, he did not then compleat the Covenant of Grace with him. This I grant, that God did then begin to deal with <hi>Abraham</hi> with reference to his eſtabliſhing his Covenant with him; did as it were draw the firſt Lines of that Covenent he intended afterwards in a more formal expreſs manner to enter with him. Hence the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> telling the Jews that they were the Children of the Covenant, cites one Promiſe then made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Acts 3.26.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Covenant recorded in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. is not the Old Covenant, nor had any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference or relation thereunto.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151884:5"/>
            <p n="3">3. That that Covenant is the Covenant of Grace, the ſame which Believers are ſtill under. And would our Oppoſers ſatisfy the World in their Judgments and Practice, they ought to return ſolid and ſatisfactory Anſwers to thoſe Arguments pleaded in Confirmation of each of thoſe Poſitions; their Silence wherein renders all their Diſcourſes utterly inſignificant in the Judgment of all Men of a competent Underſtanding. Alas! can they think a looſe Diſcourſe, however filled up with Scripture-Quotations, can be of any uſe to ſuch Perſons, ſo long as thoſe Arguments remain unanſwered? And it ſeems ſtrange to me that Men of any Judgment, Gravity or Conſcience ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to the World any Diſcourſes ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively defective in that regard, in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Cauſe they plead. It being evinced and demonſtrated paſt all rational Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, that this Covenant is not the Old Covenant, ſaid to be done away, but the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace. The moſt copious Harangue of Words, how many Scriptures ſoever are alledged therein, ſignifieth nothing, ſave only to ſhew how tenacious Men are of Error; and how they will wreſt and pervert the Scriptures, to confirm themſelves and others therein, when once embraced by them.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will ſay, There are two Treatiſes, the one of Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi>'s, the other of Mr. <hi>Philip Cary</hi>'s, wherein there are ſeveral irrefragable Arguments to prove the contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> That that Covenant is not the Covenant of Grace. To that I anſwer, It is true, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151884:6"/>there are ſuch Books abroad; but ſo long as thoſe Arguments remain unanſwered, here is only the oppoſing of Arguments to Arguments, and which are the moſt valid and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, poſſibly Men of weaker Capacities are not able to determine to the Satisfaction of their own Conſciences. Hence ſuch Methods of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure ſerve only to confirm thoſe that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reſolved, and puzzle weak conſciencious Chriſtians that are ſincerely inquiring after Truth. I ſhall only add, that the Arguments I have laid down are unanſwerable, is undoubted to me, the ſure-footing they have in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Truth aſſures me of that; neither is the Silence of our Adverſaries after their ſo long Preſentation to publick View, any ſmall Addition to that Aſſurance. I ſhall now try whether thoſe Arguments laid down by the two fore-mentioned Authors be ſo or no.</p>
            <p>To begin firſt with thoſe laid down by Mr. <hi>Grantham;</hi> he attempts to prove two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That Circumciſion was not a Goſpel-Ordinance.</item>
               <item>2. That that Covenant recorded <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. is not a Covenant of Grace. For the</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. What he means by a Goſpel-Ordinance, is to me difficult to determine; and therefore I ſhall only declare what I mean by a Goſpel-Ordinance; and in brief, I mean an Ordinance or Act of Worſhip inſtituted in the Covenant of Grace, having an immediate and direct
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151884:6"/>Reſpect thereunto, for the Confirmation, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining or conveying the Good therein pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. Now let us ſee the ſtrength of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and they are theſe three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That which could profit no Man, except he kept the whole Law, was no Goſpel-Ordinance: but Circumciſion could profit no Man, except he kept the whole Law,</hi> Ergo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And he cites <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.25. for the Proof of his Minor Propoſition.</p>
            <p>Before I anſwer to either part of his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I muſt diſtinguiſh of theſe two Terms [<hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Keep.</hi>]. Thus by Law may be meant either the Moral Law, and that taken in a ſtrict and proper Senſe, as the Law or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works, the Sum of which the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> reduces to a <hi>Do this, and live.</hi> Or,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Term <hi>Law</hi> may intend the whole Revealed Will of God concerning Man's Duty; and then under this Term Law, we are to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude both the Moral, Ceremonial, and Judicial Law, and that in their utmoſt Extent and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For that Term <hi>Keep,</hi> it may be meant either of a perfect, ſinleſs keeping, ſo as the Perſons ſo keeping the Law, ſhall live therein, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.12. Or,</p>
            <p n="2">2. It may be meant of a ſincere and upright Keeping, ſo as not willingly or wilfully to fail in doing any thing required, or doing any thing ſo bidden. Now if Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> takes theſe Terms in the firſt Senſe, (which in caſe he doth) Law here can only refer to, or be underſtood of the Moral Law, and that as a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151884:7"/>Law of Works; ſeeing God never required of, or expected from his People a perfect ſinleſs Obedience to the Ceremonial Law, no, nor to the Moral Law, as the Rule of that Obedience he requires of his People. And then I deny the Minor Propoſition, and ſay, thoſe words of the Apoſtle prove it not; and my Reaſon is, becauſe the Apoſtle there ſpeaks of the Law as conſidered under another Notion, and of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of keeping than is intended by Mr. <hi>Grantham.</hi> But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. If Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi> underſtood theſe Terms [<hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Keeping</hi>] in the latter Senſe, then I deny the Major Propoſition, and affirm on the other hand, that that (take it of Circumciſion in particular) might be and was a Goſpel-Ordinance, which yet would not profit Men except they kept the whole Law, ſeeing it might and did profit them who did ſo keep the Law. Thus the Apoſtle affirms it did profit them that kept the Law. What is here ſaid of Circumciſion may be alike ſaid of Baptiſm. It profits not thoſe that keep not the Law in the latter Senſe before-mentioned; but as for thoſe that do ſo keep the Law, it doth profit them. No Ordinance will profit any Men in caſe of their failing in that Obedience indiſpenſably required in the Covenant they are under, which is no Argument at all that it is no Goſpel-Ordinance. Goſpel-Ordinances will not profit Men, as of themſelves, in caſe they are Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, and do not walk up to that Profeſſion they make; which is all that the Apoſtle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends in that place.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:151884:7"/>
            <p n="2">2. His ſecond Argument is this, <hi>If Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion bound Men to keep the whole Law, then it was no Goſpel-Ordinance,</hi> &amp;c. Before I return an Anſwer to this Argument, I ſhall premiſe, that by Law in <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.3. which he cites to prove his Aſſumption, we are (as I ſuppoſe is granted on all hands) to underſtand the Moſaical Law, the Law given by <hi>Moſes</hi> at Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and that in the utmoſt Latitude and Extent of it. Now this Law may be conſidered two ways,
<list>
                  <item>1. As given by God to the People of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. As after miſinterpreted and miſunderſtood by them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As given by God, it had only a Subſerviency to the Covenant of Grace, and anſwerably as in it there was a Revival of the Law given to <hi>Adam</hi> in Innocency; ſo there were various Sacrifices and Ceremonial Obſervations anew inſtituted, that ſo the People, ſeeing the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs and Severity of the Law, and finding their own Inability ſo to perform it as to live therein, they might be engaged to flee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, and take hold of the Covenant of Grace confirmed, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17.) in him, whereunto they were guided by the Sacrifices, and thoſe other Ceremonial Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations. Hence the Law is ſaid to have been a School-Maſter, to bring them unto Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.24. whether we read as in our Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or only a School-Maſter unto Chriſt, it is all one, ſeeing a School-Maſter it was. Now take the <hi>Law,</hi> as thus given by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and <hi>Keeping</hi> in the latter Senſe before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151884:8"/>I grant his Aſſumption, but deny the Conſequence in the Major Propoſition; and affirm, That tho Circumciſion did bind Men to keep the whole Law during its continuance in the Church, yet it might be and was a Goſpel-Ordinance: and ſuppoſing the Apoſtle only intends this Term <hi>[Law]</hi> in this Senſe, yet he might juſtly argue againſt Circumciſion, as laying them under this Obligation to keep the Law, becauſe there was now a change and alteration in the Law. The whole Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Law was abrogated and laid aſide: and for them to put themſelves under an Obligation to keep a Law that was now abrogated, was ſinful, and would have deprived them of any Benefit by Chriſt, tho they obliged themſelves to keep it in that Senſe in which the Jews un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the firſt Teſtament were bound to keep it, and their keeping of it was acceptable to God, and profitable to themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Take the Law as miſinterpreted and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtood by the Jews, <hi>viz.</hi> as tho it had been a Law through their meer keeping of which they ſhould be ſaved, without the Mediation of Chriſt; (as it is evident they did ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it) then I deny the Aſſumption, and affirm, that Circumciſion never bound any Man ſo to keep the Law: and then the Apoſtle in arguing againſt Circumciſion, deals with the <hi>Galatians,</hi> according to that falſe Notion of the Law they had imbibed from their falſe Teachers, and tells them, that in caſe they were circumciſed, that is, as obliging themſelves to the Law in the Senſe now mentioned, they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151884:8"/>would be Debtors to do the whole Law, not only uprightly and ſincerely, but to do abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely all things written therein, ſeeing neither their Sacrifices nor Ceremonial Obſervations ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in that Law, would yield them any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, in caſe of their failing to do all things writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the whole Law, and their returning and adhering to the Law in this ſenſe, would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them of any Benefit by Chriſt. And thus I judg we are to underſtand the Apoſtle in that place: So that take the Apoſtle's Senſe which way we will, the Argument is of no force. Take the Senſe the former way, then the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence is unſound; if we take his Senſe the latter way, the Antecedent is falſe. And a greater Abſurdity can hardly be vented by Men, than to ſay, That God ever deſigned Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as an Obligation unto the Jews, thus to keep the Law, or any part of it. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. His third Argument is this, <hi>That which was always in compariſon of the Goſpel a weak and beggarly Element, was never a Goſpel-Ordinance; but Circumciſion was ſuch,</hi> Ergo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here I ſhall poſitively deny the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence in the <hi>Major</hi> Propoſition, and affirm, That that might be in the Apoſtle's Senſe ſaid to be a weak and beggarly Element; which yet, during the Firſt-Teſtament-Adminiſtration, might be a Goſpel-Ordinance. Will Mr. <hi>G.</hi> ſay, That the Jews had no Goſpel-Ordinances? Yet all their Ordinances come within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of theſe weak and beggarly Elements. Take it of the Paſſover, ſurely that was a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Ordinance,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151884:9"/>and yet one of theſe weak and beggarly Elements.</p>
            <p>But to haſten; As a cloſe of this, and to make way to what follows, I ſhall offer this one Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove, That Circumciſion was a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Ordinance, it is this, If Circumciſion was the Token of the Covenant of Grace, and as ſuch a Repreſentation and Seal to thoſe to whom it was applied of thoſe great Goſpel-Bleſſings, Righteouſneſs, Intereſt in God, and Sanctification, then it was a Goſpel-Ordinance; but the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is true, therefore the latter. I am aware Mr. <hi>G.</hi> will deny the Aſſumption; but I prove it thus, If that Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. be the Covenant of Grace, and Circumciſion was the Token of that Covenant, and, as ſuch, a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation and Seal to thoſe to whom it was applied, of thoſe forementioned Goſpel-Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, then it was a Goſpel-Ordinance.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> or Aſſumption in both Arguments, conſiſts in two Branches; both which I know will be denied: But it is the former Branch that at preſent falls under our Conſideration, and ſuppoſing that be ſufficiently proved, the latter will hardly meet with any oppoſition. Now that being already demonſtrated, I ſhall at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent add no more; only conſider what Mr. <hi>G.</hi> hath ſaid to prove the contrary, <q>That that Covenant is not the Covenant of Grace, but the Old Covenant, or that Covenant ſaid by the Apoſtle to be <hi>done away;</hi> and this he ſaith will appear three ways:</q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. From the recital of the Covenant it ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151884:9"/>
            <p n="2">2. From the Nature of Circumciſion; and chiefly becauſe the Covenant of Grace was not peculiar to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, but common to others, though they were not circumciſed.</p>
            <p>He begins with the Firſt, and thus expreſſeth himſelf; <q>Whoſoever ſhall diligently read it, (that is, the Covenant recorded <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.4 to 15.) will not find one word of the Promiſe of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs to all Nations.</q> So that it ſeems he doth not find in this Covenant, as there ſet down, any thing poſitive that makes it appear to be the Old Covenant, only Negatively he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find what he ſuppoſes ſhould have been in it. Had it been the Covenant of Grace, he cannot find one Word of the Promiſe of Bleſſedneſs to the Nations.</p>
            <p>To which I ſay, 'Tis exceeding ſtrange. Are not the Promiſes of God's being a God to the Nations, yea and with them, to their Seed; and a Promiſe of Heaven included, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally intended in the Promiſe of <hi>Canaan,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Bleſſedneſs to the Nations? What can be called a Promiſe of Bleſſedneſs, if the one or the other of theſe be not ſo? See <hi>Pſalm</hi> 144. <hi>ult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be ſaid, Theſe Promiſes are not made to the Nations, but to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed in their Generations.</p>
            <p>To that I ſay, It is granted. But then let it be remembred, That in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, all that in or from among the Nations do believe in Chriſt are intended. So that here is an expreſs Promiſe of Bleſſedneſs to all Nations, upon condition of their Believing. And upon no other Terms is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151884:10"/>that Promiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. at the beginning, made to the Nations, as Mr. <hi>G.</hi> himſelf acknowledges, <hi>pag.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>The Truth is, in that of <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. we have only a more general and indefinite Promiſe of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs to the Nations, not expreſſing wherein that Bleſſedneſs ſhall conſiſt. But when God comes in a more expreſs and formal Way to eſtabliſh his Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> as he doth in this <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. he not only promiſes Bleſſedneſs to the Nations upon their Believing, but parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly declares wherein that Bleſſedneſs ſhall conſiſt, and who among the Nations ſhall be the Subjects of it; and theſe are <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed in their Generations. Now then how any ſhould ſuppoſe that this is not the Covenant of Grace, becauſe of a ſuppoſed Defect in it of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Bleſſedneſs to the Nations, is to me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imaginable. But this is all that Mr. <hi>G.</hi> can find in the Covenant it ſelf, as a Reaſon inducing him to think it is not a Covenant of Grace, but muſt needs be the Old Covenant: Whereas the Reaſon why he cannot find what he looks after, is, becauſe he will not ſee it: and indeed none ſo blind as they that will not ſee.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He argues from the Subjects of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. And he argues thus; <q>If the Covenant of Circumciſion had been the Covenant of Grace, and Circumciſion the Sign of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, then had all true Subjects of it, as ſuch, been new Creatures in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: but the true or right Subjects of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, (I ſuppoſe he means this Covenant)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151884:10"/>and Sign as ſuch, were not new Creatures in Chriſt Jeſus.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Before I return an Anſwer to this Argument, I ſhall only ask Mr. <hi>G.</hi> this one Queſtion, and that is, Whether he judges, that to be a New Creature in Chriſt Jeſus, was indiſpenſably ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the Salvation of Men under the Firſt Teſtament? If he ſay it was, then I deny his <hi>Minor</hi> Propoſition, and affirm on the other hand, That all the true and right Subjects of this Covenant, (I mean of ſuch as were of ripe Years) ought to have been New Creatures, and then as ſuch had the Promiſes to them in their Generations, including their Infants with themſelves. If Mr. <hi>G.</hi> ſay it was not neceſſary, then I ſhall only ſay, Let him ſay what was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to their Salvation, the ſame was neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their Admiſſion into this Covenant, and having the Token of it applied unto them. But for a further Anſwer to this Argument, I ſhall refer the Reader to my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> p. 98, &amp; 117.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He argues from the Author of <hi>Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> And thus he conceives Circumſion could not <q>be a Goſpel-Ordinance, becauſe (as he thinks) <hi>Moſes</hi> gave it as an Obligation to keep the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial Law.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Mr. <hi>G.</hi> ſeems to be proving, That the Covenant of Circumciſion could not be the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace; but here he returns to prove, That Circumciſion was not a Goſpel-Ordinance. But let us ſee the Strength of his Reaſoning. He had before argued from the Obligations Circumciſion brought Men under to keep the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151884:11"/>whole Law: So that the Strength of this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon lies only in this, That it was given by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> and this he would prove from <hi>John</hi> 7.22. where ſaith our Lord Chriſt, <hi>Moſes gave you Circumciſion.</hi> But let it be obſerved, that our Lord Chriſt himſelf qualifies that Aſſertion, and therefore immediately adds, <hi>Not becauſe,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as I judg, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there ſhould be read; not that, or not as though Circumciſion was of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> and ſo here is a plain denial that Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was of <hi>Moſes.</hi> And hence when our Lord Chriſt adds, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. <hi>If any Man on the Sabbath receive Circumciſion, that the Law of</hi> Moſes <hi>ſhould not be broken;</hi> he ſeems evidently to deal with the Jews according to their own Sentiments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Circumciſion. They looked upon it as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the Ceremonial Law; but ſaith Chriſt, <hi>It was not of</hi> Moſes, <hi>but of the Father.</hi> However (for this is of no great Conſideration) it is certain, Circumciſion was long before <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:</hi> It was given to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and that as the Token of the Covenant of Grace, and ſo might and did continue, although on the account of ſomewhat Ceremonial in it, it was inſerted in the <hi>Sinai</hi>-Covenant; and anſwerably the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was repeated by <hi>Moſes.</hi> But for further ſatisfaction to this, ſee my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Cox,</hi> p. 117. But,</p>
            <p n="4">4. There is yet one thing more that Mr. <hi>G.</hi> ſeems to lay great weight upon, and that is this; <q>That the Covenant of Grace was not pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his, but common to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, though they were not Circumciſed.</q> Which after he expreſſeth thus; <q>The Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151884:11"/>to be circumciſed, was peculiar to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and to his Seed or Family, in ſuch a ſenſe, as none but they were obliged to be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But to that I would ſay, I grant, That the Covenant of Grace might be common to others, though they were not circumciſed, as Mr. <hi>G.</hi> himſelf affirms. But yet I would willingly know, how far Mr. <hi>G.</hi> will extend that Term <hi>[Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly],</hi> whether he only intends <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Lineage or Poſterity; and ſo Seed and Family are of an equal extent. And if he thus under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that Term <hi>[Family],</hi> then how notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly falſe his Aſſertion is, is obvious unto all. But if he extend it to all that were adopted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Family, as thoſe bought with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or born in his Houſe, and the Proſelites; how the reſtraining Circumciſion to them ſhould in the leaſt intimate, and much leſs prove, That that Covenant was not the Covenant of Grace, nor Circumciſion a Goſpel-Ordinance, is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to imagine. But that which I ſuppoſe he drives at, is this, There were ſome in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace which were not circumciſed, nor under an Obligation to be circumciſed. Now in Anſwer to this, I would only demand of Mr. <hi>G.</hi> Whether he is ſure the Covenant now entred with <hi>Abraham,</hi> was ſo far promulgated, as that the Perſons he talks of had knowledg of it? Or ſuppoſe they had ſome notice of it, Whether their Duty to be circumciſed was made known unto them? Either of theſe things being gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, how their not being circumciſed, ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate that this Covenant is not the Covenant
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151884:12"/>of Grace, nor Circumciſion a Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, is as much above the Reaſon of Man to apprehend as the former. I would commend to Mr. <hi>G.</hi> the Caſe of <hi>Cornelius</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 10. the latter end.</p>
            <p>There is only one thing more that I would take notice of in Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s Diſcourſe. And thus he argues againſt that Covenant, its being a Covenant of Grace, from the Date of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. But I have returned ſo ſatisfactory an Anſwer to that in my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Cox,</hi> that I ſhall and no more; ſee <hi>p.</hi> 97, and ſo on.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now come to what Mr. <hi>Cary</hi> hath ſaid in purſuance of the ſame Deſign, namely, to prove, That that Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. is not the Covenant of Grace, but on the other hand, that it is the Old Covenant, or a Covenant of Works: only I ſhall premiſe, that at preſent I deſign not a full Anſwer of his Book; that I have already done in my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Cox.</hi> Neither do I know how I could more effectually anſwer his Book, than by laying down and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thoſe three Propoſitions there laid down and proved.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now only take notice of what is Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentative in his Book, and conſidering the Commendation it hath by Five (as I ſuppoſe) of the chiefeſt of that Perſwaſion, and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatory Epiſtle by a Sixth, I might juſtly expect ſomething extraordinary; and I ſhall not deny but that my Expectations were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what high. But if ever that Proverb, <hi>Partu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riunt Montes,</hi> were verified, it is here. Alas!
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151884:12"/>what do I meet with but <hi>Ridiculus Mus?</hi> For I have yet obſerved but two Arguments ſyllogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically framed, by which he attempts the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of his Notion, and the very recital of them may, in the judgment of all unbyaſſed Perſons, be a ſufficient confutation of them.</p>
            <p>There firſt is in his <hi>p.</hi> 120. and it is this; <q>If that Covenant (he means that recorded in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.) was as much a Covenant of Works as that Covenant of Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and that Covenant mentioned <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.9. nay, as much as the Covenant made with <hi>Adam</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Fall; then it is not a Covenant of Grace: But it was as much a Covenant of Works as either of the Covenants before-mentioned were; Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>A luſty Argument, if it would ſtand. But truly I might with ſorrow ſay, as the Apoſtle, of ſome, that would be teachers of the Law, <hi>There are ſome that would be Teachers of the Goſpel, neither knowing what they ſay, nor whereof they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm.</hi> But to the Argument:</p>
            <p>I poſitively deny the <hi>Minor</hi> Propoſition, as that concerns the Covenant made with <hi>Adam,</hi> and that entred with the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> at Mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> As for that Covenant mentioned <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 'tis the ſame with this in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> both which I affirm to be one and the ſame Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Cary</hi> attempts to prove his <hi>Minor</hi> thus; <q>It muſt needs be as much a Covenant of Works, as that entred with the People at Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> yea as that made with <hi>Adam</hi> in Innocency; becauſe although God promiſed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151884:13"/>to be a God to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, yet it was upon condition of Obedience, with an anſwerable Threatning.</q> But can Mr. <hi>Cary,</hi> or any other Man of common ſenſe, think that the bare requiring of Obedience in any Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, or Threatning of Judgments in Caſe of Diſobedience, makes it preſently a Covenant of Works? Is it not expreſly ſaid, That <hi>our Lord Chriſt is the Author of Salvation to all that obey him?</hi> and doth he not ſay, <hi>according to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace?</hi> Yea, and is not Faith it ſelf an Act of Obedience, and yet the Condition of the Covenant of Grace? Mr. <hi>G.</hi> expreſly grants that it is; and (if I do not miſtake) ſo doth Mr. <hi>Cary</hi> alſo. And for Threatnings, doth not the Apoſtle tell us, <hi>If we live after the Fleſh, we ſhall die?</hi> Rom. 8.13. Yea, doth not our Lord Chriſt give us the Sum of the Goſpel-Covenant, in his Commiſſion to his Apoſtles, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. and yet doth he not ſay, <hi>He that believeth not, ſhall be damned?</hi> But not to waſte time, Mr. <hi>Cary</hi> muſt know, that it is not the bare requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Obedience, nor yet the denouncing Threatnings, that makes a Covenant a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works, but the commanding a perfect ſinleſs Obedience to all that is written therein, and threatning Death unto all, in caſe of the leaſt failure in ſuch an Obedience. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to proceed. His,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Argument, which is of a like validity with this, we have, <hi>p.</hi> 204. and it is this, <q>That Covenant in which Faith was not reckoned to <hi>Abraham</hi> for Righteouſneſs, could never be a Covenant of Faith, (of Grace I ſuppoſe he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151884:13"/>means).</q> And this Argument he takes to be ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtible. Strange Confidence! And not to ſpend Time in ſhewing the Inſufficiency of his Proof, that ſpeaking of Circumciſion when his Argument ſpeaks of the Covenant; and ſure there is a wide difference between the Covenant, and Circumciſion the Token of it. So that this Argument of it ſelf falls to the ground for want of Proof. But yet let me ask this one Queſtion of Mr. <hi>Cary,</hi> and that is, Whether Faith was reckoned to <hi>Abraham</hi> for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by a meer Act of Soveraign Grace, without Reſpect had to any Covenant he was then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? Or, was it reckoned to him by virtue of ſome Promiſe of any Covenant that he was then under? If he ſay the former, Then I ſhall only ſay, how his having his Faith reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him for Righteouſneſs, by ſuch an Act of Soveraign Grace, ſhould be an Argument that this Covenant after entred with him, was not the Covenant of Grace, is above the reach of Man's Underſtanding to apprehend. But if he ſay the latter, then I ſhall affirm, That was the Covenant of Grace; the ſame for ſubſtance with this now entred with him, only before leſs compleat, but now fully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated: and how the Inſtitution of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion could either caſt <hi>Abraham</hi> out of it, or alter the Tenure of the Covenant, ſo as that before he had Faith reckoned to him for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, by virtue of the Promiſes contained in it, but after neither had nor could have Faith alike reckoned to him for Righteouſneſs by virtue of the ſame Promiſes, is as much
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151884:14"/>above the Underſtanding of Man as the former.</p>
            <p>We will ſuppoſe an <hi>Heathen</hi> or a <hi>Pagan</hi> converted and enabled to believe: Now upon his very firſt Converſion and Believing, he hath his Faith reckoned to him for Righteouſneſs; but afterwards this Man is baptized, ſhall we now ſay that the Covenant he is received into, and of which Baptiſm is a Sign or Seal, neither is nor can be the Covenant of Grace, becauſe he had his Faith reckoned to him for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs before his Baptiſm, or while in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized Condition; how abſurd would that be? So that this Argument is ſo far from being ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtible, that it hath not the leaſt weight in it. But to proceed. Having removed out of our way theſe feeble Argumentations, whereby theſe two Authors endeavour to prove, That that Covenant <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. is not the Covenant of Grace, but the Covenant of Works, (the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect contrary whereunto I have affirmed) whereby the Arguments I have laid down for the Proof of my Aſſertion, may be rendred ſomewhat doubtful in the Judgments of Perſons of weaker Capacities, ſeeing Propoſitions lying ſo diametrically oppoſite the one to the other cannot both be true. I doubt not thoſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments laid down by me will be ſeen in their full force.</p>
            <p>And therefore I ſhall return to my firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, which is (as I have ſaid) to direct to the laying a ſure Foundation to the Practice of Infant-Baptiſm in this Covenant eſtabliſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Seed in their Generations.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:151884:14"/>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing then to be done is, to determine the true and proper Subjects of this Covenant.</p>
            <p>The firſt (as I have ſaid) is convincingly to prove, that it is indeed the Covenant of Grace, the very ſame Covenant under which Believers ſtill are.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing (I now ſay) is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the true and proper Subjects of it: And that they are and were <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed in their Generations, the very words of the Covenant do aſſure us; for ſo the Covenant runs, <hi>I will eſtabliſh my Covenant between me and thee, and thy Seed after thee, in their Generations.</hi> Here let it be obſerved, That it is not ſaid, <hi>I will eſtabliſh my Covenant between me and thee, and thy Seed in thy Generations,</hi> but <hi>between the and thee, and thy Seed in their Generations, to be a God unto thee and thy Seed.</hi> Now the Queſtion is, Who we are to underſtand by <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed? and who are intended and included in that Phraſe, <hi>Their Generations?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, I anſwer, That by <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, we are undoubtedly to underſtand all that is Scripture bare that Denomination of his Seed: And theſe are of two ſorts, 1. His Natural Seed. And, 2. His Spiritual Seed. All thoſe who through their taking hold of, and Reception into this Covenant, were, or are adopted into his Family, as the Proſelytes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the firſt Teſtament, and Believers under the New. As for Believers under the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (whom at preſent we are only concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in) that they are to be accounted as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151884:15"/>Seed, is expreſly according to the Letter of the Scripture; <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. Now I ſay, this Covenant God promiſeth to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh between Himſelf and <hi>Abraham,</hi> and all his Seed, whether Natural or Spiritual: Here is no Exception of the one or the other kind of his Seed, but the words are abſolute, <hi>I will eſtabliſh my Covenant between me and thee, and thy Seed after thee, in their Generations:</hi> And when God makes no Exception, we ought to make none.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But who are intended and included in this Clauſe <hi>[Their Generations]?</hi> Who are theſe Generations of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed? To that I ſay, they are the natural Infants, or natural Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed. And that we are to underſtand the Infant-Seed naturally deſcending from this Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> I have (as I hope) ſufficiently proved formerly, and have as yet met with no Contradiction. And indeed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we include the Infant-Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed in that Clauſe, <hi>[Their Generations]</hi> there can be no Reaſon aſſigned of God's adding it; nor can it be interpreted in any other Senſe, in a Conſiſtency with the Truth and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of God in his Covenant. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. That which is to be done in purſuance of the End mentioned is, to ſettle and eſtabliſh the true Tenour of this Covenant, as here eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd between God and <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Seed in their Generations. And for this we muſt obſerve that this Covenant, as here eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, may be conſidered two ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As having a more general Reſpect to all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:151884:15"/>
            <p n="2">2. As having a peculiar and ſpecial Reſpect to thoſe who heretofore did, or yet do ſtand immediately related to him as his Seed. Such were the Children immediately deſcended from his own Loins, as <hi>Iſaac, Iſhmael,</hi> &amp;c. and ſuch are his Spiritual Seed, <hi>viz.</hi> Believers: they ſtand in as an immediate Relation to <hi>Abraham,</hi> as his Seed immediately deſcending from his own Loins did: And the Covenant, as eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed with theſe, gives them a preſent actual Right to, and Intereſt in the Good promiſed in it. And for the more clear underſtanding the true Tenour of this Covenant, theſe three things muſt be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Covenant was and is eſtabliſhed between God and all theſe his immediate Seed, univerſally one as well as the other. That it was ſo eſtabliſhed between God and <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Seed, I have fully proved; and that it is ſo eſtabliſhed between God and his Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Seed, will certainly be readily granted by all that lay claim to this Spiritual Relation unto <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That it was and is eſtabliſhed between God and every one of theſe that were or are the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> in their Generations, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding (as I ſaid) their Infant-Seed with their Parents, between God and whomſoever this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant hath been eſtabliſhed, it always hath been, and is eſtabliſhed between him and them in their Generations: this is according to the expreſs words of the Covenant: So that ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to be granted (as I judg it is paſs'd all ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Contradiction proved) that in that Clauſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151884:16"/>
               <hi>[Their Generations]</hi> the natural Infants of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>'s Seed are included, it muſt be granted, that all the Infant-Seed of Believers are (as ſuch) in Covenant with God, and anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly have a preſent Right and Title to the Good promiſed in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That this Covenant indiſpenſably requires a perſonal Acceptation of, and Cloſure with it, by all between God and whom it hath been or is eſtabliſhed. As for grown Perſons, their firſt Admiſſion into it doth indiſpenſably require it: as for Infants, whether naturally deſcended from <hi>Abraham,</hi> or from his Seed, ſuch a perſonal Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of and a Cloſure with it, always hath been and is indiſpenſably required upon their coming to Years of Diſcretion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they did and do become <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Seed; and as ſuch convey Covenant-Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to their Seed. And from theſe three things we may infer theſe two Colloraries.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Poſterity im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately or mediately deſcending from him, did, as grown up to Years of Diſcretion, hold their Intereſt in the Covenant, and Right to the Good promiſed, not as his Natural Seed, but as his Spiritual Seed. And the like muſt be ſaid of Believers Seed, I mean of ſuch who have their Covenat-Intereſt continued to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That however the Covenant might have a more general Reſpect to all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Seed mediately deſcended from him, yet none of them could merely as his Natural Seed, lay a juſt Title to the Covenant, nor did the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151884:16"/>Covenant ſecure to them any part of that Good contained in it. Their Parents failing to take hold of the Covenant, did forfeit both their own and their Childrens Intereſt; the like is ſtill true under the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In purſuance of the ſame Deſign, the Terms of the Covenant including both the Stipulations or Promiſes made on God's part, and the Reſtipulation or Duty required of thoſe with whom it is made. And this Stipula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on God's part in the general conſiſts in theſe two Promiſes:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he would be a God to them. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he would give them the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> including and principally intending the Heavenly Inheritance, <hi>viz.</hi> Heaven it ſelf. So that whoſoever God doth enter this Covenant with, as he engages himſelf to be a God to them, ſo to give them the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> either literal <hi>Canaan,</hi> or the Heavenly Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance typified thereby. And hence theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes being made both to <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his Seed in their Generations, including both Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Children, it ſufficiently appears, that the Good, or the Benefits and Bleſſings accrew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Infants by their Covenant-Intereſt, are vaſtly more than meerly Nominal, as Mr. <hi>Cary</hi> will ſtill needs ſuppoſe them to be. But ſee my Eſſay, <hi>p.</hi> 99, to 163.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Reſtipulation on the part of thoſe with whom this Covenant is entred in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral is, that they keep the Covenant, ſo <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.9. And for a more clear underſtanding of this, and the improvement of it to the End
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151884:17"/>mentioned, theſe four things muſt be carefully obſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That by <hi>Keeping</hi> the Covenant is firſtly intended, the Application of the Token, Sign or Seal of the Covenant, and that as obliging to the performance of the whole of what God requires of thoſe 'tis entred with. <hi>Token,</hi> here we muſt not take abſtractly in it ſelf, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding its Uſe and End. And hence,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Under this Command, <hi>To keep the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> is required the performance of all that Duty ſpecified in the Covenant, according to the Capacity of the Subjects of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That this Command, as more generally laid down, obligeth all the Subjects of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant univerſally: and anſwerably as it ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth Parents, ſo their Seed; as it obligeth all them taken into Covenant under the firſt Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, whether of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Natural Seed, or Proſelytes, always including Parents and Children, ſo it ſtill obligeth <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Spiritual Seed, <hi>viz.</hi> Believers, ſtill including Parents and Children. And hence,</p>
            <p n="4">4. We muſt neceſſarily diſtinguiſh between this Command as more generally expreſs'd, and the Deſignation of the Token to be kept. The Command is abſolute, and extends to all <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Seed in their Generations, and being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver repealed, muſt needs extend to Believers under the New Teſtament, and that in their Generations, that is, both Parents and Children: So that tho there hath been an alteration in the Token of the Covenant, it was formerly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151884:17"/>Circumciſion, but now Baptiſm, yet the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is the ſame, that ſtill abides in its full force; and anſwerably here we have an expreſs Command for the Baptiſm of the Infant-Seed of Believers, tho not <hi>eo nomine</hi> as Baptiſm, yet as the Token of the Covenant: as take the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand abſtractly by it ſelf (as we ought to do) it did not require Circumciſion <hi>eo nomine</hi> as Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, but as the Token of the Covenant. God firſt gives out a Command to keep his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, intending, though not only, yet prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, the Token of it; and as ſo given out, it obligeth all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed in their Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whether thoſe under the firſt, or Believers under the ſecond Teſtament: and then he ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifies what ſhould then be the Token of it, and that was Circumciſion. But when our Lord Chriſt comes in the Fleſh, he lays aſide that Token, and intimates another, which is Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm: but the Command to keep the Covenant, as abſtractly taken, abides in its force through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Ages. This indeed our Oppoſers ſeem unwilling to underſtand: but let things be ſeriouſly and impartially weigh'd, and Truth will appear and prevail.</p>
            <p>Laſtly; In purſuance of this Deſign, the Scriptures muſt be throughly ſearch'd, and whatever is found in them for the further Diſcovery, and aſſuring us of the Mind and Will of our Lord Chriſt, relating to the Practice under Conſideration, muſt be taken in, and improved for this End and Purpoſe. The full Mind and Will of our Lord Chriſt is not held forth in a ſingle Scripture, or in any
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151884:18"/>part of the Scriptures, but the Revelations of it lie ſcattered throughout the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and whoever will make a thorow and impartial ſearch, they will find much, poſſibly much more than yet hath been brought to light, clearly manifeſting and aſſuring us, that this is indeed his Mind and Will, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Infant-Seed of Believers, as taken into the ſame Covenant with their Parents, ſhould be baptized. Thoſe that ſee meet, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe what I have written of this import in thoſe ſmall Tracts, here referred to. And to ſum up all in brief, If any Man ask me what War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant I have to baptize the Infant-Seed of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers? they may take it thus:</p>
            <p n="1">1. I find that that Covenant recorded <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. was a Covenant of Grace, the very ſame Covenant under which the Church and People of God ever ſince have been and ſtill are. This to me is paſt all rational Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I find that God did eſtabliſh this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant between himſelf and <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Seed in their Generations.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I find that in this Clauſe <hi>[Their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations]</hi> the Infant-Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed were and are univerſally included.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I find that this Covenant, as actually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying a preſent Intereſt in, and Right to the Good contained in it, did only extend to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s immediate Seed, whether thoſe naturally deſcended from him, or thoſe who became his Seed by taking hold of the Covenant, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably that all his mediate Seed held their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151884:18"/>in the Covenant, not as his Natural (tho many of them were ſo) but as his Spiritual Seed; as having perſonally taken hold of the Covenant themſelves. And,</p>
            <p n="5">5. I find that this Covenant was always en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, whether Natural or Spiritual, in their Generations, including their Infants with the Parents. It was ſo du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Firſt-Teſtament-Adminiſtration, and anſwerably muſt needs be alike ſo under the New.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I find that God did expreſly command, that both <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed in their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, ſhould keep this Covenant, intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby, tho more, yet firſtly, that they ſhould obſerve and apply the Token of it, as Parents ſhould have it applied to themſelves, ſo that they ſhould take care that it be applied to their Children as Joint-Heirs of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes with themſelves.</p>
            <p n="7">7. I find that Baptiſm is the preſent Token of the Covenant; and conſequently is the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken now to be applied by virtue of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, obliging all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed in their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations to keep the Covenant. And,</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I find variety of other Scriptures fully aſſuring me, that I do rightly underſtand his Mind and Will as thus revealed in his firſt eſtabliſhing this Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Father of the Faithful, and his Seed in their Generations. And from the whole, I would now ask, Where are thoſe far-fetch'd Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences that our Oppoſers talk of, that we are forced to make uſe of for the Proof of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151884:19"/>Infant-Baptiſm? Let but <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant be rightly underſtood, taking in all other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures confirming the Practice we plead for, and here will be found no other Conſequences, than what are neceſſary to a right Uſe and Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any Command or Promiſe whatſoever contained in the Scriptures: And what ſhould hinder then, but that this Controverſy at laſt ſhould come to a Period?</p>
            <p>I have only further to touch in brief upon a Sheet of Paper lately come forth, in oppoſition to the Practice of Infant-Baptiſm, by an <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymous</hi> Author; the deſire of ſome that I ſhould return an Anſwer unto which, hath occaſioned the foregoing Pages. Who the Author is, I have as yet no intimation: I ſhall only ſay, That if he be one that hath aſſumed the Work of a Teacher among the Men of his Perſwaſion, he hath done prudently in concealing his Name; but if he be a private Member of any of their Congregations, (as I ſuppoſe he may be) he might have made himſelf known. For who will expect from any, more than they have received, or might juſtly be expected to have attained to? He ſeems to be (and I hope is) one of thoſe for whom I have heartily wiſhed that they had a greater ſhare in thoſe Abilities, that ſome of that Perſwaſion have attained to. But (be he who he will) he attempts to prove theſe two things:</p>
            <q>
               <p n="1">1. That Baptiſm ought to be adminiſtred univerſally, by Dipping or Plunging the whole Body under Water.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:151884:19"/>
               <p n="2">2. That grown Perſons profeſſing their Faith and Repentance, are the only true Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Baptiſm.</p>
            </q>
            <p>As to the firſt, I ſhall ſay but little, did not he, or any other of his Perſwaſion, make that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Baptizing ſimple and abſolutely neceſſary to the Truth and Validity of that Ordinance, and annul it when otherwiſe adminiſtred, they ſhould meet with little oppoſition from me. I doubt not but Baptiſm, as ſo adminiſtred, is true Baptiſm, and was (at leaſt ſometime) ſo adminiſtred in Primitive Times, and a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Time after; but that our Lord Chriſt doth indiſpenſably require it to be ſo admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred univerſally, that I deny: and doubt not but that Baptiſm adminiſtred, either by pouring Water on, or waſhing the Face with Water, yea, or ſprinkling Water upon the Face, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the right Form of Baptiſm to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, is true Baptiſm, and valid to all its Ends and Purpoſes, and need not be repeated: and I judg that our Lord Chriſt expreſſeth Baptiſm by a Word that will admit of a different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of adminiſtring it. But for this I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer this good Man, and all others that deſire Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, to my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Danvers,</hi> pag. 143, to the end. All that he hath added to what others have ſaid, is an Obſervation he hath made, that in the <hi>Dutch</hi> Teſtament, <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> is called <hi>John the Dooper.</hi> But of how little Conſideration that is, is obvious unto all: The utmoſt that can be made of it is only this, That one Man, or at leaſt very few that tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated the Bible into <hi>Dutch,</hi> judged it beſt ſo to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151884:20"/>render the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and what ſignifieth the Judgment of One, or a few Men? Suppoſe our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlators had ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred it <hi>John the Waſher,</hi> (as they might have done) would this Man have taken their Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation as a certain Determination of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy? But I ſhall refer the Reader to the Place mentioned: as alſo to Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of this Subject, the beſt that I judg is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. And if any be yet unſatisfied, they have the liberty from me to act according to the Light they have received, provided they do not plead the Manner of Adminiſtring that Ordinance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the dueneſs of Infant-Baptiſm. The Manner of adminiſtring that Ordinance, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns not the Subjects of it. Whence it is moſt unreaſonable and abſurd to plead the Manner of Adminiſtring Baptiſm againſt our Practice. Let the Subjects be determined, and let every one act according to his own Light in the Manner of Adminiſtring that Ordinance.</p>
            <p>But to proceed; The other Thing that he attempts to prove, is, <q>That only grown Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, profeſſing Faith and Repentance, are the true Subjects of Baptiſm.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And as for this I ſhall not ſay much: Thoſe that will impartially peruſe and weigh what I have already ſaid, (they imitating the Noble <hi>Bereans,</hi> Acts 17.) will (as I judg) ſee it whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly needleſs. Indeed, for ſuch as Mr. <hi>Grantham,</hi> who cannot ſee Bleſſedneſs promiſed to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in that Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of their diſcerning the Mind and Will of our Lord Chriſt contended about, though ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151884:20"/>in the cleareſt Noon-Light of Divine Revelations. But for thoſe who have Eyes to ſee Truth when brought to Light, I ſhall not be ſo uncharitable to ſuppoſe, that what this Honeſt Man hath ſaid, will raiſe the leaſt Heſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in their Minds about the Intereſt of the Infant-Seed of Believers in the Covenant, or their Right to Baptiſm on the account of that their Intereſt. But yet let us take a brief view of what he hath ſaid to prove his Aſſertion. And he attempts to prove it three ways.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. From Scripture.</item>
               <item>2. By Reaſon grounded upon Scripture.</item>
               <item>3. From certain Abſurdities which he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes will follow upon our Practice.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. For Scripture. And thus he would prove his Aſſertion two ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the Scriptures recording the Baptiſm of grown Perſons, without making mention of the Baptiſm of their Infants. And he Inſtances in thoſe that were baptized by <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> the Diſciples of Chriſt, and <hi>Philip.</hi> To which I will ſay only two Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Suppoſing that ſome of them had Infants, How doth our Author know but that they were baptized, though the Scripture records it not? We find no record of the Apoſtles Baptiſm, and yet undoubtedly they were baptized. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suppoſe that they had Infants, and they were not Baptized, that doth not at all preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the Cauſe of Paedobaptiſm. For let it be conſidered that all theſe, excepting the Eunuch, who undoubtedly then had no Infants, at leaſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151884:21"/>with him, whoſe Baptiſm we have now reſpect unto, their Infants as well as themſelves had been before circumciſed: and the Parents might, and it was neceſſary they ſhould be baptized, but their Children might not, neither was it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that they ſhould, having already the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Covenant applied to them, which as yet was not laid aſide.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſaid, So had their Parents. But to that I ſay, 'Twas neceſſary that their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ſhould be Baptized, as an Obligation to, and whereby they did in a ſpecial manner viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly own and acknowledg, That that very Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>viz.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, was the true Meſſias pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to their Fathers. Hence it is no way ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, nor the leaſt prejudice to the Cauſe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm, to grant, that none of the Infant-Seed of believing Jews, till the abſolute abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and laying aſide of Circumciſion, was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed and fully, made known to the Church, were baptized: But now after the Reſurrection and Aſcenſion of Chriſt, when Circumciſion was wholly laid aſide, we ſtill find when Parents were Baptized, their Houſholds, peculiarly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding their Children, were Baptized with them. But it may be our Author will ſay, he doth not argue meerly from the Scriptures not mentioning the Baptiſm of Infants, but from that taken in Conjunction with <hi>John</hi>'s Preaching Repentance, and Chriſt's making Diſciples by teaching them, and the Apoſtles requiring Faith of thoſe that they Baptized. But to that I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; Both <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> our Lord, and the Apoſtles, having to do with grown Perſons, they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151884:21"/>did, and it was neceſſary they ſhould preach Repentance, teach and inſtruct them before they baptized them, and upon their profeſſing their Faith and Repentance, adminiſter that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to them: But what is that to Infants? They might have, and had, by virtue of their Parents Faith, an Intereſt in the Covenant, and upon that account had a right to Baptiſm, which when Circumciſion was laid aſide, and Baptiſm inſtituted, was applied to them. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. He would prove his Aſſertion from the Commiſſion given by our Lord Chriſt to his Apoſtles. But to that, having ſo fully proved that the Commiſſion doth not exclude, but on the other hand include Infants, ſuppoſing their Intereſt in the Covenant, and yet the fitneſs and meetneſs of our Lord Chriſt's expreſſing the Commiſſion as he hath done, that it is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuperfluous to add any thing more. See my <hi>Plain Proof of Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> p. 73. as alſo my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Danvers,</hi> Chap. 2. p. 25. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall proceed.</p>
            <p>Our Author offers two Reaſons why Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is by Dipping, Waſhing, or burying the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy all over in Water, only to Believers upon a profeſſion of their Faith and Repentance.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <q>That it is the Poſitive Law and Soveraign Will and Pleaſure of God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In Anſwer to which: As to the Manner of Adminiſtring Baptiſm, which his two Reaſons ſeem to have a peculiar reſpect unto, having ſpoken to that already, I ſhall add no more, but take his Reaſons as reſpecting the Subjects of Baptiſm; and as to this Firſt I ſay, in a direct
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151884:22"/>Oppoſition to what he ſaith, That it is not the poſitive Will or Pleaſure of God, that Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers only ſhould be baptized, but it is alike his poſitive Will and Pleaſure that their Infants ſhould be baptized with them. This I have ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved, which I refer him unto; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to his</p>
            <p>Second Reaſon, and that is taken from two Ends of Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>To which I ſay, that there are other Ends of Baptiſm, with reference to which it is the Will and Pleaſure of God that it ſhould be applied to Infants. To inſtance only in theſe two:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That by it they may be by a ſolemn Right or Ordinance of his own Inſtitution, dedicated, given up, and engaged unto God in Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in and by it, the Benefits and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of the Covenant may be repreſented and ſignified, and the Promiſes wherein they are contained, ratified and confirmed, both to Parents and Children, which when they come to Years of Maturity, they are to improve, as to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, ſo to engage themſelves perſonally to cloſe in with the Covenant, and give up themſelves to God in Chriſt, according to the Tenour of it; and thereupon ſtrengthen and confirm their Faith in a believing Application of the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to themſelves. Hence what he ſaith of all Worſhip, which he ſaith is not commanded by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in his Holy Word, is vain Worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It concerns not us, ſeeing we affirm it is according to the Will of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in his Word, That Infants ſhould be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. But,</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:151884:22"/>
            <p n="3">3. He argues from certain Abſurdities, which (as he ſuppoſes) will follow upon our Practice. Of which I muſt ſay in the General, that they are all mere Miſtakes and Scare-Crows, the Effects of a clouded Fancy. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That we go to <hi>Moſes</hi> for an Inſtitution of Baptiſm. When as we go not to <hi>Moſes,</hi> but to the Covenant of Grace eſtabliſhed with our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed in their Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and confirmed of <hi>God</hi> in Chriſt, 430 Years before the Law was given by <hi>Moſes.</hi> For his Second, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That our Practice lays a Foundation for a National Church: 'Tis ſtill a groſs Miſtake. 'Tis well known that there are in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>New-England,</hi> who plead for and live in the Practice of Congregational Churches, and yet maintain the Doctrine and Practice of Infant-Baptiſm, and that in a perfect conſiſtency with their Principles and Practice. For the Third, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That it affirmeth the Children of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, were by Virtue of their Parents Faith in the Covenant of Grace, united or ingrafted into Chriſt, contrary to <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>But that our Practice ſhould contradict the Apoſtle, in that <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. where all are ſaid <hi>to be Children of Wrath,</hi> which are the Words, I ſuppoſe, he hath reference to; ſuppoſing our Principles rightly underſtood, is unimagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. Yea, it is becauſe we believe them to be Children of Wrath as well as others, that we ſo earneſtly contend for their Covenant-Intereſt, and the Dueneſs of their Baptiſm up
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151884:23"/>on the Account thereof. They may be, and are, Children of Wrath by Nature, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſinned in <hi>Adam,</hi> and being ſhapen in Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and conceived in Sin; and yet upon their Birth into the World, be, as the Seed of Believing Parents, taken with their Parents into the Covenant of Grace; and hereupon have a Right to be implanted into Chriſt's Myſtical Body, whereby they are ſecured, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their pure Infant-State, from the Effects of that Wrath they were by Nature the Children of: And who can aſſign any ſhew of Reaſon, why it may not be ſo? They are not the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Wrath, and in the Covenant of Grace, at one and the ſame inſtant of Time: their State, as Children of Wrath, precedes their State, as in Covenant with God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As for the Fourth Abſurdity, it's deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Souls; I ſhall only ſay, That if any ſuch thing doth happen, 'tis from the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or neglect of Parents, or thoſe that ſhould inſtruct them. We only affirm, That their Covenant-State ſecures them from the Effects of Wrath during their pure Infancy. The Covenant indiſpenſably requiring their perſonal Faith and Repentance, when they come to Years capacifying them to Believe and Repent. And what Deceit is here put upon any? For his</p>
            <p>Laſt Abſurdity, that ſtill is but his own Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, proceeding from his Ignorance of the true Doctrine of Infants Covenant-Intereſt and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. Will he but peruſe what I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in my <hi>Eſſay,</hi> p. 143. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he may ſee this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151884:23"/>Abſurdity fully removed out of his Way. But,</p>
            <p>Laſtly, This Our Brother (for ſo I ſhall own him) comes to anſwer ſome Objections againſt what he hath ſaid.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As for that Objection he raiſeth from what we are taught concerning the Doctrine of Baptiſm in the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> not being concerned in it, I ſhall ſay nothing to it. But for his,</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Object.</hi> I ſhall briefly touch upon that, and haſten to a cloſe. 'Tis raiſed from the Pleas we make for Infant-Baptiſm, from the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed in their Generations. And as a Reply to what he ſaith in Anſwer to this Objection, or theſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections: he pretends to anſwer Two Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, the One raiſed from <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. the Other from <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. But they may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into One. I ſhall referr him, and all others, to what I have written, to ſhew the Sureneſs of the Foundation laid in this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant entred with <hi>Abraham</hi> for the Practice of Infant-Baptiſm, a Summary of which may be ſeen in the fore-going Pages: and ſhall only take notice of what he ſaith of a Covenant of Election, unto which both <hi>Abraham,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was called, and alſo many Children, both of Believers and of Unbelievers, did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long. But as to that I ſay, That a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Election is a meer <hi>Chimaera:</hi> there is no ſuch thing revealed in the Scriptures. That there is an Election of Grace, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle is expreſs; but of a Covenant-Election
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151884:24"/>we find not the leaſt mention throughout the Scriptures: and poſſibly our Author means no more than what we affirm. Which if it be ſo, I ſhall let the Unſcripturalneſs of his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion paſs: but ſhall affirm, That none, whether Old or Young, ever were, are, or ſhall be (ſo far as is revealed unto us) ſaved meerly by virtue of their Election. I ſhall not determine what Reſerves God hath kept ſecret in his own Breaſt concerning the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Infants deſcending from wicked Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, whether Heathens or nominal Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: Secret things belong unto God. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the Caſe of ſuch Infants at all concern the preſent Controverſy. But this I ſay, According to what is revealed in the Scriptures, None ever were, are, or ſhall be ſaved by virtue meerly of their Election; but all that are ſaved (ſo far as God hath revealed unto us) muſt be, and are ſaved by Virtue, and according to the Tenour of the Covenant of Grace, <hi>viz.</hi> This Covenant eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed with <hi>Abraham</hi> as the Father of the Faithful, and his Seed in their Generations. Hence I ſhall aver (how cruel ſoever I may be judged to be by Mr. <hi>Grantham</hi>), That no Unbeliever can, according to any Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, have any aſſured Hope, either of their own, or of their Childrens Salvation who die in their Infancy. But this is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy excentrical to my preſent Deſign, neither do I deſire to engage in it. This I am ſatisfied in, That all the Seed of Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, at leaſt that do own their Childrens Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-Intereſt,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151884:24"/>and do not, out of contempt to the Ordinance of God, neglect their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, are infallibly ſaved (if they die in Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy); as for others, let the Day declare it. As for him that will undertake to reprove God, in caſe he do not ſave all Infants, I ſhall only ſay as God himſelf doth in a like Caſe, <hi>Let him anſwer it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to have done. As for what our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor enlargeth upon that Suppoſition, That that Covenant entred with <hi>Abraham,</hi> was the Old Covenant, it is utterly inſignificant, ſeeing I have ſo fully proved, That that Covenant is not the Old Covenant, nor had any Relation to it, but indeed is the Covenant of Grace, that Covenant-Believers are ſtill under, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have no Reaſon to take any notice of it.</p>
            <p>As for what he ſaith in Anſwer to that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether Baptiſm came in the Room or ſtead of Circumciſion? It is enough for us, that Baptiſm is the Token or Seal of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; (which our Author acknowledges,) and anſwerably doth correſpond with, and come in the ſtead of Circumciſion, in the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Notion of it, <hi>viz.</hi> as the Token of the Covenant. Hence whatever other Differences may be aſſigned, they concern not this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy.</p>
            <p>I have only this to deſire of this good Man, That he will be perſwaded that he hath not as yet looked half the way into this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy. And ſhall add, that if any will yet agitate this Controverſy, I earneſtly beg of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151884:25"/>them to do it, ſo as to approve themſelves unto him that ſearcheth their Hearts, and is ready to judg the Quick and the Dead, and ſhew themſelves to be Men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>The Author hath publiſhed theſe Treatiſes alſo about this Subject, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. INfant Baptiſm from Heaven, and not of Men; or a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Diſcourſe concerning the Baptiſm of the Infant-Seed of Believers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Infant-Baptiſm from Heaven, and not of Men, the <hi>2d</hi> Part: Or an Anſwer to <hi>Mr. Danvers</hi>'s Treatiſe of Baptiſm. Wherein Infants Right to Baptiſm is further confirmed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. An Eſſay to revive the Primitive Doctrine and Practice of Infant-Baptiſm, in the Reſolution of Four Queſtions. 1. What are the Reaſons of God's appointing the Token of his Covenant to be applied to the Infant-Seed of his People. 2. What is the Good or Benefit they receive thereby. 3. What is the Duty of Parents towards their Children, as bearing the, Token of the Covenant. 4. What is the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement that Children, as grown up to Years of Maturity, may and ought to make of the Token as applied to them in their Infancy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Infant-Baptiſm plainly proved. A Diſcourſe wherein certain Select Arguments for Infant-Baptiſm, formerly ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtically handled, are now abbreviated, and reduced to a plain Method for the Benefit of the Unlearned. With a large Epiſtle to the Pious and Learned among the <hi>Antipaedobaptiſts,</hi> eſpecially the Authors of the late Confeſſion of their Faith.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A brief Diſcourſe concerning Man's natural proneneſs to, and tenaciouſneſs of Errors. Whereunto are added, ſome Arguments to prove, That that Covenant entred with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> Gen. 17.7. is the Covenant of Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All ſold by</hi> Jonathan Robinſon <hi>at the Golden-Lion in St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s Church-Yard. Together with ſeveral other Treatiſes in Defence of Infant-Baptiſm, by Mr.</hi> Baxter, <hi>Mr.</hi> Wills, <hi>Mr.</hi> Barret, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:151884:25"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A POSTSCRIPT:</hi> Being a further Defence of <hi>INFANT-BAPTISM,</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Keach.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHEN the foregoing Sheets were juſt wrought off the Preſs, a little Tract came to my hand, put forth by Mr. <hi>Benjamin Keach,</hi> one of the Epiſtolers to Mr. <hi>Cary</hi>'s Book, which I have peruſed; and although I find not my ſelf, in the way wherein I have proceeded, farther proof of Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm much concerned; neither do I fear but that any who ſhall truly weigh what I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, will ſee what he hath ſaid is ſufficiently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viated, and therefore I might well, and at firſt view of his Book, have thought to have let it paſs without taking any notice of it. Yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is poſſible ſomething that he hath ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, or rather repeated from others, may ſomewhat obſtruct Perſons of weaker Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in their compliance with that Practice I have pleaded for; I have, upon ſecond thoughts, judged it meet to conſider what he hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſo far as I conceive neceſſary; for I would not willingly leave any thing behind me unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved out of the way of the weakeſt of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtians, complying with the Mind and Will of our Lord Chriſt, in reference unto that practice wherein his Intereſt and Kingdom, the Glory of God, the Good of Children, and the Comfort of their Parents, is ſo nearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151884:26"/>and the rather, becauſe our Lord Chriſt ſeems in a ſpecial manner to have allotted me, with ſome others, the maintaining of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince: And it may not be unuſeful, at leaſt to Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> himſelf, to remark ſome few things in the general, before I come to a particular conſideration of what he hath ſaid; and,</p>
            <p>Firſt, It may be remarkable how confident he is, when the Grounds he proceeds upon are ſo ſlight and trivial, and which have been afore fully removed, giving us too much ground to ſuſpect, he hath as yet looked but a very little way into this Controverſy. How ſlight and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial his Grounds are, and where he might have ſeen them before removed, ſhall be ſhewed after. Yet ſee how he expreſſes himſelf, <hi>pag.</hi> 65. in an <hi>Apoſtrophe</hi> to our Lord Chriſt; <q>Lord, ſays he, that Man ſhould be ſo bold and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous, as once to attempt to alter or change any thing (he hath reſpect unto the Subject of Baptiſm) of this Holy or great Commiſſion, or adventure to do things contrary to what is given forth here by Jeſus Chriſt, as King and Law giver of the New Teſtament.</q> When he might, and it is ſomewhat hard for me to perſwade my ſelf, that he hath not ſeen it ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved, that in the Pleas we make for Infant-Baptiſm, we make not the leaſt alteration or change in that Commiſſion, but affirm that it was neceſſary, that although it be the Will of Chriſt that Infants ſhould be baptized, yet he ſhould expreſs himſelf therein as he hath done. I ſhall only ſay at preſent, it's eaſy, and not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual for Men, Cynick-like, by crying out of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151884:26"/>other's ſuppoſed Evils, to diſcover the ſame more prevailing in themſelves.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It may be remarked, how partial he is in his own Cauſe; it appears that he takes it for granted, as indeed we all do, that Chriſt hath power to preſerve, protect, and uphold all grown Perſons, in their being Baptized by Dipping or Plunging, how aged, weak, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm ſoever they are, and that in the coldeſt Climates, and ſharpeſt Seaſons; and he would perſwade himſelf, yea, is very confident, none ever received the leaſt hurt or damage by being ſo baptiz'd, (yea, he concludes, as he may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do, That our Lord Chriſt would not inſtitute any Ordinance to deſtroy the Lives of any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) thus <hi>pag.</hi> 66. and yet he pleads it as an Evidence, <q>That Infants cannot be the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Baptiſm, becauſe their tender Bodies cannot bear it in theſe cold Climates without palpable danger of their lives.</q> And tells us again, <q>That Chriſt never appointed any Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance to deſtroy the lives of any of his Creatures;</q> thus Page the <hi>4th</hi> of his Epiſtle, and 32d of his Book. But let me ſay, Why cannot Jeſus Chriſt preſerve, protect, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Infants, as well as grown Perſons, whoſe Age, Weakneſs, and Infirmities, in conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the tender and delicate way and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of living, renders their Bodies alike ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as, if not more tender than the Bodies of Infants, and whoſe Baptiſm by Immerſion would as palpably in danger their lives, as the Immer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Infants would indanger theirs. But it ſeems, in the conceit of our Author, that is an
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151884:27"/>Argument againſt the Subjects of Baptiſm, which is none againſt the manner of baptizing, when as the thing it ſelf is indeed as ſtrong an Argument againſt the one, as againſt the other: And for mine own part, were there a neceſſity of Baptiſm by Immerſion, I could as eaſily truſt our Lord Chriſt with the preſerving the lives of Infants, as of grown Perſons, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as thoſe aforementioned: But our Author here gives as a hint why they ſo zealouſly plead for baptizing by Immerſion, it is, that they might exclude Infants from Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I cannot but remark Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> his great diſingenuity, (that is the mildeſt term I can give it) for indeed 'tis very bad, exceeding bad, and a very great diſparagement, both to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Cauſe. I ſhall only give a two-fold Inſtance: Firſt, in his quoting Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and other Paedobaptiſt Aſſertions, concerning the Uſe and End of Baptiſm, and the Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Subjects to be baptized, as though they were contradictory unto their practice; whereas what they ſay, is indeed no way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory thereunto, but fully conſiſtent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; and in particular, as for Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> he hath fully vindicated himſelf, which yet Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> hath the ingenuity to take no notice of: And it is certain, the Uſe and End of Baptiſm are not ſuch, but that it may be fitly applied to Infants; and how unreaſonable and abſurd is it to conclude, that becauſe ſuch and ſuch Qualifications are required in the Adult, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Infants are not to be baptized? that there were certain Qualifications required in the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151884:27"/>Adult Heathens to their Circumciſion which their Infants were uncapable of yet, and that their Infants were circumciſed with them, is undeniable. Now ſuppoſe any of the Prieſts or Levites, whoſe Lips were, as the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaks, to preſerve Knowledg, ſhould preach or write of thoſe Qualifications; for any from thence to conclude againſt the circumciſing their Infants, how abſurd would it be? It may be our Author will ſay, they had an expreſs Command for their Circumciſion. To which I anſwer, It is granted, and we affirm that we have, if not an expreſs Command, yet that which is equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent thereunto, for the baptizing of Infants: of which more immediately.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly.</hi> Our Author's Diſingenuity appears in his frequent Citations out of Mr. <hi>Danvers</hi> Book (a Book of which it muſt be ſaid, it hath been and for ever will be a Reproach to the Cauſe it pleads; and I cannot but hope himſelf hath repented, as others of that Perſwaſion are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of it) without taking notice of the Anſwers long ſince returned unto it; yea, ſuch is the Diſingenuity of our Author, that he cites ſome Teſtimonies againſt Infant-Baptiſm, which have been paſt all Contradiction, proved to be meer Falſhood and Forgeries, take that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>pag.</hi> 91. where he quotes the <hi>Magdebur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſes,</hi> as cited by Mr. <hi>Danvers.</hi> It is true, our Author has the Wit to leave out part of Mr. <hi>Danvers</hi>'s pretended Citation, wherein that Falſhood did particularly lie, but he has the Diſingenuity to conceal part of what thoſe worthy Authors ſay, which had he produced,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151884:28"/>would have quite ſpoiled their Teſtimony, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they poſitively affirm, that Infants as well as the Adult, were in Primitive Times baptized. Now how Men of any Conſcience can uſe ſuch diſingenuous Methods, is to me a Riddle. I ſhall only add, <hi>O my Soul, enter not thou into their Secrets.</hi> But to come to the Book: as for what he ſays in his firſt Chapter, we are fully of the ſame mind with himſelf; the four next Chapters are wholly taken up in Attempts to prove, that it's only Baptiſm by dipping or plunging the whole Body into Water, which is true Baptiſm. I ſhall not ſay much to this, having already given a clear account of the Grounds on which I judg that our Lord Chriſt hath not indiſpenſably tied up his Church to that manner of adminiſtring that Ordinance, which Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> may conſider if he pleaſe. At preſent I ſhall only obſerve a few things in thoſe Attempts made by our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and paſs on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I cannot but obſerve how he will needs oppoſe Rantiſm or Sprinkling, to Dipping, or Plunging, or immerging the whole Body under Water, as tho that were, if not the only, yet the main and moſt principal uſed manner of Pedo-Baptiſts adminiſtring that Ordinance: hence he ſtrenuouſly applies himſelf to prove that there is a difference between <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> cannot ſignify to ſprinkle; and this I ſuppoſe he doth <hi>ad faciendum populum,</hi> ſeeing he cannot but know that many, if not moſt, or all Pedo-baptiſts, eſpecially who conſcienciouſly make the Word their Rule, adminiſter that Ordinance by waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151884:28"/>or pouring Water upon the Face of the Party baptized, whether Infant or Adult.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It may be obſerved, That whereas our Author inſiſts ſo much upon the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to prove that baptizing muſt neceſſarily be by ſlipping or plunging under the Water, and that as eſſential unto true Baptiſm: It is certain, and himſelf acknowledges it, that this word is of a large Signification: Firſt, It ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies to Die, and this ſeems to be its firſt and moſt native Signification. This ſome of his own Authors, and others might be mentioned, do affirm; and anſwerably it ſignifies to plunge, <hi>Tingendi cauſa,</hi> in order to Dying or giving ſome new Colour; the primitive word being taken from a Dyers Fat. Hence we read in Prophane Authors <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>tingere lanas,</hi> to die Wool; ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, double-dyed Purple. Hence it will follow, that barely to dip or plunge into Water, is not the firſt or primary Signification of the Word; It notes ſomething more than a bare dipping or plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging into Water; it notes ſuch a Dipping or Plunging as whereby the thing dipped or plung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed may receive a new Die or Colour which it had not before. <hi>2ly,</hi> It ſignifies barely to dip or plunge, and it ſignifies dipping or plunging; becauſe things died are dipped or plunged into that Liquor or Liquid Matter they are dyed in. <hi>3ly.</hi> It ſignifies to waſh, ſo Mr. <hi>Lee</hi> (one of the Authors cited by Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>) tells us, that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Heſychus, Stephanus, Scapula</hi> and <hi>Budeus,</hi> the great Maſters of the Greek Tongue, make good, by very many Inſtances and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151884:29"/>Allegations out of Claſſick Writers, importeth no more than Ablution or Waſhing; ſo that according unto theſe great Maſters of the Greek Tongue, Ablution or Waſhing, is as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roper a Signification of this word, as dipping or plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging. Hence for any to argue meerly from the Signification of the Word, is exceeding weak, and utterly unconvincing. But,</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly.</hi> It may be obſerved, that whereas our Author ſaith, that when it ſignifies Waſhing, it is ſuch a Waſhing as is done by dipping ſo much as is waſhed; it muſt be ſaid it is otherwiſe. Take it only of waſhing the Hands, tho other things might be mentioned, ſo the waſhing the Hands or the Feet of the Prieſt under the Law is included in thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, mentioned <hi>Hebrews</hi> 9.10. compared with <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.18. So the Phariſees waſhing their hands before Meat, is called <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,</hi> Luk. 11.38. where it's ſaid they mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled that he, meaning Chriſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that he had not been baptized. Now it is certain in waſhing their Hands they did not always, if ordinarily, dip or plunge them into the Water, but had Water poured upon them: ſee 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.11. So that the word, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording unto its uſe in the Scripture, may be rendred very fitly to waſh; and ſignifies ſuch waſhing, as is by pouring Water on the Party or Subject waſhed. I ſhall not fear to affirm, that the waſhing one Part of the Body by pouring Water, is according to the Scripture-Acceptation of the word, true Baptiſm. Doctor <hi>Owen,</hi> who underſtood the Greek as well as moſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151884:29"/>in his Day, if not as any in any former Age, tells us, That Baptiſm is any kind of waſhing, whether by dipping or ſprinkling, putting the thing to be waſhed into the Water, or applying Water unto it, ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10. And how invalid then is his Argument taken from the bare ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the word.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4thly.</hi> It may be obſerved, that whereas our Author tells us, that Dr. <hi>Du-Veil</hi> affirms, that the conſtant Practice of the Univerſal Church till about the Year 1305, was to baptize by Immerſion, it muſt be ſaid, that ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> doth faithfully cite him, he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a very great Miſtake, the contrary may be evidenced paſt all rational Contradiction, only to inſtance in thoſe at preſent, called <hi>Clinici,</hi> which were ſuch as were baptized on their Beds, of whom we read at leaſt 1000 Years before that; and hence note,</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5thly.</hi> The utter Improbability that our Lord Chriſt ſhould bind up his Church to ſuch a manner of adminiſtring this Ordinance, as would neceſſarily exclude many thouſands from it, or expoſe them to apparent danger of Life, as in the caſe of Infants, the dueneſs of whoſe Baptiſm I hope hath been ſufficiently proved; ſo in the caſe of Perſons in extream old Age un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der lingring Sickneſs and Weakneſs, eſpecially ſuch who have lived Valitudinarian Lives all their days; but he ſeems evidently to have uſed this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which admits of different Modes of adminiſtring this Ordinance, either by dipping, or plunging, or waſhing, whether by pouring Water upon the Subject, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151884:30"/>applying Water unto it, and a liberty of adminiſtring it either way, hath conſtantly been maintained in the Church.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only further note, in the laſt place, that whereas our Opponents generally inſiſt upon <hi>John</hi> 3.23. where the Evangeliſt gives the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>John</hi>'s baptizing in <hi>Aenon,</hi> to be the muchneſs of Water being there; and it muſt be granted, they are ſomewhat countenanced in their Notion by our late Annotators, and ſome others; this I would ſay, that neither the Learned Annotator upon that Book, nor our Brethren ſeem duly to conſider the Original, for it is not, there was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> much Water, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> many Waters, many Streams or Rivolets of Waters; and Travellers tell us they were ſo ſhallow as not to reach above the Ankle, (ſee <hi>Sandys</hi> Travels) ſo that the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt giving that as the reaſon of <hi>John</hi>'s baptizing there, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe there were many Waters, ſeems rather to imply that ſeveral were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in baptizing, than that Baptiſm was adminiſtred by Immerſion, the ſmall quantity of Water there hardly admitting that way of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring the Ordinance. But I deſign Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and anſwerably ſhall refer both our Author and all others to what I have ſaid in my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Danvers,</hi> and alſo to Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of this Subject afore referred unto, and come to the main Controverſy between us and our Brethren, and that concerns the Subjects of Baptiſm. And I call this the main Controverſy, becauſe neither my ſelf, nor, ſo far as I know, do any Pedo-baptiſts deny the Validity of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151884:30"/>Baptiſm by Immerſion; neither ſhall I deny that Baptiſm was ſometime ſo adminiſtred in Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Times; that it was always ſo is altogether uncertain; yea, there is a very great probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity that it was not. See our new <hi>Annotations,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> often cites upon <hi>John</hi> 3.23. Therefore, I ſay, the main Controverſy is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Subjects of Baptiſm; and the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, Whether only Adult Believers are the Subjects of this Holy Sacrament? or, Whether their Infant-Seed are not the joint Subjects of it with themſelves? The former is affirmed by our Brethren, we affirm the latter. Our Author attempts to prove the former Two ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. More laxly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. More Strictly and Syllogiſtically. And what he ſaith in a more lax or looſe Way, he afterwards reaſſumes and forms into Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And therefore, I ſhall paſs that by, and the rather, becauſe I have already fully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viated all that he ſaith in my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Danvers,</hi> who argues from the very ſame To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks that our Author doth, (which he might have, and I ſuppoſe hath ſeen, tho' for Reaſons that may be gueſſed at by others, but are beſt known to himſelf, he hath taken no notice of) and come to his Arguments; the four firſt of which are but a repetition of what he had in a more lax or looſe way formed up into Syllogiſms, ſo that I might juſtly paſs them alſo by, but yet briefly to touch upon them.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is this; <q>If there be no Word of Inſtitution, nor any thing in the Commiſſion of Chriſt, for the baptizing of Infants, but of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151884:31"/>Believers only; then not Infants, but Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers only ought to be baptized: but the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is true, therefore the latter.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I find Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> himſelf takes (as he ought to do) Authority from Chriſt, equivalent to a Word of Inſtitution, or the expreſs men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Infants in the Commiſſion. And that being granted, I deny his <hi>Minor</hi> Propoſition, and affirm, That we have full Authority from Chriſt to baptized Infants. This I have ſo fully and demonſtratively proved already, (ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what I have ſaid in proof of it, may be ſeen in the foregoing Sheets) that it is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous to add any thing more. I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that they are joint Subjects of the Covenant with their Parents, and as ſuch, the proper Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Baptiſm. If Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> will ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily anſwer the Arguments I have offered, he will do both the Church of God and my ſelf no little Service.</p>
            <p>As for what he adds in confirmation of his <hi>Minor</hi> Propoſition, it is meer trifling; in brief, it is this, <q>'Tis evident and owned by the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, That thoſe who are enjoined to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in the Commiſſion, are firſt to be taught, or made Diſciples.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To which I ſhall ſay, Suppoſe we have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Authority from Chriſt to baptize Infants, how evident ſoever it be, that thoſe who are enjoined to be baptized, are firſt to be taught and made Diſciples, we have ſufficient Warrant for their Baptiſm, that Authority of our Lord Chriſt is our Warrant.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:151884:31"/>
            <p n="2">2. We ſay, that Infants are Included in the Commiſſion. All that are to be baptized, their Baptiſm is enjoined in the Commiſſion: But In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are to be baptized, <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c. As for thoſe Learned Men he ſpeaks of, if he means that they own, That all thoſe univerſally who are enjoined to be baptized, muſt be taught, or made Diſciples, he muſt certainly intend the Learned of his own Perſwaſion; which now few they are, is ſufficiently known; neither is it of any great concern what they own or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own in this Controverſy. As for others, what they own, concerns only the Adult; which makes nothing againſt the baptizing of Infants, whoſe right to Baptiſm comes in another way, <hi>viz.</hi> from their Covenant-Intereſt, as having the Promiſes made unto them as the Seed of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving-Parents. And as for what our Author ſays in Anſwer to that Objection of ſome Paedo-Baptiſts, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>That Children are part of the Nations commanded by Chriſt to be baptized,</q> I ſhall paſs it by (not being concerned at all in it) and proceed;</p>
            <p n="2">2. He Argues from the Scriptures requiring Faith and Repentance, as Prerequiſites of all them that are to be baptized.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſhall only ſay, this requires better Proof than what our Author hath here given; which I ſhall expect <hi>ad Graecas Calendas.</hi> He only cites <hi>Acts</hi> 2.36, 37. and <hi>Acts</hi> 8. I ſuppoſe he hath reſpect to the <hi>37th</hi> Verſe, and an Anſwer to a Queſtion in the <hi>Rubrik;</hi> but to how little purpoſe, is obvious unto all. That Faith and Repentance are required as Prerequiſites of all
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151884:32"/>the Adult that are to be baptized, is granted; but that they are required of all univerſally, neither is nor can be proved. Therefore to paſs this, and,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Sum and Subſtance of his Third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is this, <q>As there is no Precept, ſo no Precedent in Scripture, that any beſides ſuch as profeſſed Faith and Repentance were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, therefore not Infants; but only ſuch ought to be baptized.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In Anſwer whereunto, I doubt not it hath been fully proved, that we have a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept for Infant-Baptiſm. See my <hi>Infant-Baptiſm from Heaven,</hi> Firſt Part, <hi>pag.</hi> 114. And beſides the other Revelations our Lord Chriſt hath made of his Will, are obliging and equivalent to a Precept. And this being granted, That becauſe there is no Precedent in Scripture that any Infants were baptized, therefore they ought not to be baptized, is a <hi>non ſequitur;</hi> a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept is enough without any Precedent. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſay, We are not altogether without Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents: Thus, in all thoſe Houſholds that were baptized, when yet only the Parents, or chief Governors, are recorded to have belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His Fourth Argument is this, <q>Becauſe <hi>Paul,</hi> who declared the whole Counſel of God to the Churches, and Primitive Chriſtian, never declared any thing of Infant-Baptiſm; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are not to be baptized.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſhall not at preſent enquire how, or in what ſenſe <hi>Paul</hi> is ſaid to have declared the whole Counſel of God. Two things I would only ſay:</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:151884:32"/>
            <p n="1">1. That it is certain, ſo far as the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>Paul</hi> made of the Counſel of God are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in Scripture, he did not declare abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and univerſally his whole Counſel. This is too evident than to need proof: neither is it abſurd to ſay, that the Apoſtle declared much more of the Counſel of God, than what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in any of his Sermons or Epiſtles, it being contained in other parts of Scripture. And for the Pen-men of the Holy Scriptures, to have ſet down the whole of what every Prophet, or our Lord Chriſt, or any of his Apoſtles declared to the Churches, had been ſuperfluous: 'tis enough that the whole Counſel of God is contained in one or another part of the Scriptures; and we are ſure they contain this part of his Counſel, that Infants ought to be baptized. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſay, that the Apoſtle did declare ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, yea, much of this part of his Counſel. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. He declares, That if either Parents are Believers, then their Children are Holy, that is, Holy foederally.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Paul</hi> declared, That the Infant-Seed of Believers do appertain to the Myſtical Body of Chriſt. He expreſly declares, that that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. was made unto Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. that is, Chriſt Myſtical; and that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe extended unto Infants, it being made to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed in their Generations, (as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore proved) and this the Apoſtle perfectly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He declares this as part of the Counſel of God, that all that appertain to this Myſtical
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151884:33"/>Body, ought to be admitted or incorporated there into by Baptiſm. This is doubt not but Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> will readily grant.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He argues thus; <q>Whatſoever is neceſſary to Faith or Practice, is left in the written Word, or made known to us in the Holy Scriptures: but Infant-Baptiſm is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein; therefore Infant-Baptiſm is not of God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Argument hath been already ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently anticipated. I ſhall only ſay at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, That Infant-Baptiſm is contained in the Scriptures; and muſt ſay, the Reaſon why our Adverſaries ſee it not, is their too evidently ſhutting their Eyes againſt that Light held forth unto them: Hence all our Author's Quotations are impertinent, ſoeing we ground our Practice upon the Scriptures. Let our Author ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorily Anſwer what we have ſaid, and then let him triumph. But,</p>
            <p n="6">6. He argues thus; <q>If no Man or Woman, at any Time or Times, were by the Almighty God, Jeſus Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles, neither commended for baptizing any one Child, or Children, nor reproved for neglecting to baptize ſuch; then Infant-Baptiſm is not of nor from God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Argument our Author ſeems to have borrowed from Mr. <hi>Ives;</hi> and he might have ſeen it ſufficiently baffled long ſince: See my <hi>Infant-Baptiſm from Heaven,</hi> Firſt Part, <hi>p.</hi> 300, to 310. I ſhall only add, as it is formed by Mr. <hi>Keach,</hi> That the Conſequence in the <hi>Major</hi> Propoſition needs proof. Why ſhould we im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151884:33"/>upon the Spirit of God? Is it not enough that he hath revealed our Duty? What neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity is there that he ſhould leave upon Record a Commendation of any for the Practice of it, or a Diſcommendation for the Neglect of it? And therefore for our Author to ſay as he doth, <hi>pag.</hi> 69. is exceeding weak. He ſhould have proved that it is univerſally true, with reſpect to all Goſpel-Duties, at leaſt Ordinances: and that it muſt neceſſarily be ſo, let him produce a Commendation given to any Woman for parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipating in the Lord's Supper, or Diſcommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for the Neglect of it. But not to ſtay upon ſuch Trifles.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Our Author argues, from a ſuppoſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, <q>That the Doctrine and Practice of Infant-Baptiſm make upon the Honour, Care, and Faithfulneſs of Jeſus Chriſt, our Bleſſed Mediator, and Glorious Law-giver; he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes they render him leſs faithful than <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the New Teſtament in one of its great Ordinances, nay Sacraments, to lie more dark and obſcure in God's Word, than any Law or Ordinance in the Old Teſtament did, and therefore cannot be of God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But to this, I ſay, Our Lord Chriſt hath perfectly revealed his Will relating to this practice; and it muſt be ſaid, it is from the Darkneſs and Ignorance, if not wilful Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Opponents, that they do not, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will not ſee it, and conſequently doth not at all reflect on the Honour, Care, or Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt, it rather reflects upon themſelves; and this I ſhall add to ſpeak, with utmoſt holy fear and trembling in ſuch tremendous Matters,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151884:34"/>that it had vaſtly more reflected upon the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Care, and Faithfulneſs of our Lord Chriſt, had he not declared his Will to us, that Infants ſhould not be Baptized, ſuppoſing that had been his Will, then his revealing it no plainer than he hath done, when it is his Will that they ſhould be Baptized doth: But for this, ſee my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Danvers,</hi> pag. 56, &amp; 57.</p>
            <p>But to come to our Author's laſt Argument, which is this; <q>That Ordinance God has made no Promiſe to Perſons in their Obedience thereto, nor denounced any Threatning or Puniſhment on ſuch who ſlight, neglect, and contemn it, is no Ordinance of God; but God has made no Promiſe to Perſons that Baptize their Children, nor denounced no Threatning nor Puniſhment; therefore Infant-Baptiſm is no Ordinance of God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As previous to an Anſwer to this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it may be inquired what Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> means here by an Ordinance of God? if he means any Act or Part of Worſhip that is contra-diſtinguiſhed from all other Acts or part of Worſhip, as preaching the Word is an Ordinance contra-diſtinguiſhed from the Celebration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments; then I ſhall readily grant his Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and do affirm, That Baptiſm, as applied to Infants, is not diſtinct Ordinance from Baptiſm as applied to grown Perſons, no more than Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm as applied to Women, is a diſtinct Ordinance from Baptiſm as applied to Men; or as it is applied to young Men, is a diſtinct Ordinance from Baptiſm as applied to old Men; 'tis not any Conſideration or Circumſtance relating to the Subjects of an Ordinance, that makes that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151884:34"/>an Ordinance diſtinct from the ſame Ordinance, as the Subjects of it fall under other Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Circumſtances; Circumſtances relating to the Subjects of Ordinances, diverſifies not Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. And therefore if Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> underſtand this Term Ordinance in this ſence, let him make the utmoſt he can of his Argument, we are not concerned in it. But, <hi>2dly.</hi> If he mean by Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, any Duty injoyned by God reſpective to his Ordinances, take it of Baptiſm in particular; then I deny the Conſequence in his Major Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and affirm, That that may be a Duty, unto the Performance of which no particular, explicite or expreſs Promiſe is made, or againſt the Neglecters or Contemners of which no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular or explicite Threatning is denounced; 'tis enough that God hath revealed our Duty, and promiſed Rewards in the general to the Obedient, and denounced Threatnings and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments on the Diſobedient; and how many Duties might be mentioned that have no parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, explicit or expreſs Promiſe made to the Performance of them, nor any ſuch Threatning or Puniſhment denounced againſt thoſe that neglect or contemn them. But to haſten, having, tho briefly, yet I hope ſatisfactorily ſhewed the Invalidity, yea Vanity of theſe Reaſonings of Mr. <hi>Keach,</hi> to prove, that the Adult are only the proper Subjects of Baptiſm; I ſhall now briefly conſider what he hath ſaid to inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidate our Argument for Infant-Baptiſm taken from the Covenant entred with <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 17.7. which, he rightly ſaith, is the main and great Argument which we bring for our Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. Indeed he in reciting our Argument
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151884:35"/>hath confuſedly jumbled ſeveral things together, which I ſuppoſe he will not find ſo jumbled together in any Pleader for Infant-Baptiſm: In brief, our Argument is this; If the Infant-Seed of Believers are in common with their Parents the true and proper Subjects of the Covenant of Grace, then they are the true and proper Subjects of the Token of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which now is Baptiſm: but the former is true; therefore the latter. Now let us ſee what our Author has ſaid to this Argument; and it may be obſerved, that he doth not at leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly deny that Covenant to be the Covenant of Grace, yea, implicitly he grants it ſo to be, wherein he leaves, if not the moſt of thoſe who, eſpecially of late, have pleaded the ſame Cauſe with himſelf: I ſuppoſe he hath ſeen the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsfulneſs of their Attempts, and therefore was not willing <hi>perdere oleum</hi> in proving what he knew could never be proved. But he offers four things to invalidate our Argument: 1. He ſaith, and is very poſitive, That this Covenant was not made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Carnal (he ſhould have ſaid Natural) Seed according to the Fleſh: But that it was made with him and his Spiritual Seed, and ſuch who had the Faith of <hi>Abraham.</hi> And he ſeems greatly to wonder that all Men ſhould not be convinced by thoſe three Scriptures compared together, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. &amp; 29.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.8. that is, to ſee how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently he expreſſeth himſelf, <hi>pag.</hi> 100. one would think the Apoſtle might be believed in his expounding that Text, meaning that in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. <hi>Pag.</hi> 106. when he had feigned an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection that ſome might make, which he thus
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151884:35"/>frameth, <q>Say what you will, the Promiſe and Covenant of Grace was to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Natural Off-ſpring. He returns this Anſwer, Why, Do you not believe the Apoſtle who tells you the quite contrary?</q> So once again, after he had cited thoſe fore-mentioned Scriptures, he adds, <q>Could the Apoſtle in plainer terms have detected the Error of theſe Men?</q> he means thoſe who ſay that Covenant was made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his See according to the Fleſh. Strange Confidence! But who ſo blind as they that ſhut their Eyes? But in Reply unto this, I ſhall only ſay, Or Author lies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a double Miſtake; the former is about what we affirm, the latter about the mind and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtle in thoſe places. 1. The Miſtake he lies under about what we affirm, is this; he ſuppoſes we ſay, that that Covenant was made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his Natural Off-ſpring, whether immediately or mediately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from him meerly as they were his Natural-Off-ſpring, whereas both my ſelf and many others, both formerly and of late, do affirm, that that Covenant was actually entred only with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Natural Seed, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately proceeding from his own Loins, and that all his Natural Seed mediately deſcended from him, held their Intereſt in the Covenant, either as his Spiritual Seed, or as their Infant-Seed; and that <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Natural Seed immediatly deſcending from his own Loins, were taken into this Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf, is made evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent paſt all rational Contradiction: See my Infant-Baptiſm from Heaven, firſt Part, <hi>Pag.</hi> 2. and ſo on; neither doth the Apoſtle in any of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151884:36"/>the places mentioned in the leaſt contradict this.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our Author miſtakes about the mind and meaning of the Apoſtle in this Scripture, he ſuppoſes that he excludes both <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Seed, whether immediate or mediate, as alſo the Infant-Seed of all Believers, from this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and the Promiſes of it, which never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Thoughts of the Apoſtle to do. As for that in <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.7, 8. ſee my Infant-Baptiſm, <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. throughout, where I have proved that the Apoſtle is ſo far from excluding <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> or any Believer's Natural Seed from this Covenant, or any Promiſes of it, that as to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s immediate Natural Seed he neceſſarily ſuppoſes their Intereſt in it. And for <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16, 29. I ſhall only ſay, that in caſe that Covenant was entred with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Natural Seed immediately deſcending from him, and all his Spiritual Seed in their Generations, including their Infants with them, which I have demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated that it was; the Apoſtle is ſo far from excluding them, that it's paſt all rational Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction he doth include them; the Promiſe is made unto Chriſt, that is, Chriſt Myſtical, as our Author himſelf acknowledges, but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, in their Generation, including Infants with their Parents, therefore will we believe the Apoſtle, Infants with their Parents are included in that term <hi>Chriſt;</hi> it is Chriſt Myſtical, including himſelf as Head, <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed in their Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that the Covenant was entred with: For the Lord to ſay unto <hi>Abraham, I will be a God unto thee, and unto thy Seed, in their Generations,</hi> is all one, as the Apoſtle Expounds it, as to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151884:36"/>ſay, I will be a God unto Chriſt; ſo that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and his Seed in their Generations, ſtill including himſelf as Head, conſtituted and make up Myſtical Chriſt. Now then thoſe two Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes of our Author being rectified, his firſt Conſideration vaniſhes, and makes not the leaſt head of Oppoſition againſt our Arguments. But, 2. he puts a Suppoſition that we could prove all the Children of Believers to be in that Covenant made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> yet our Author thinks it doth not from hence follow, that they may be baptized, unleſs we can ſhow the Lord Chriſt has injoyned them ſo to be. But to this I would ſay, Would he really grant this, the main of our Controverſy were at an end. And will he grant this, as will he yield unto Truth he muſt do, then I ſhall refer him to theſe three Arguments I have laid down to prove, That they not only may, but ought to be baptized. See my Infant-Baptiſm, <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 9. Till which Arguments are anſwered, which Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> may do at his Leiſure, if he pleaſes, it is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ſuperfluous to add any more. We ſhall not deny what he hath ſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> That it's not enough to ſay Children are in the Covenant, therefore they ought to be baptized: yet let me ſay, this would carry a fair probability in it; but this I ſay, If our Lord Chriſt hath aſſured us, that it is his Will that being in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant they ought to be baptized, as thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments fully prove he hath; Then that is enough to warrant our Baptizing of them. Hence as to our Author's two other Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they only deſigning the Confirmation of this Aſſertion, I ſhall ſay nothing eſpecially
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151884:37"/>having touched upon what he ſaith in them in my Anſwers to Mr. <hi>Grantham,</hi> and therefore ſhall come to a Cloſe, not finding my ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in his Anſwers to the other Scriture-Proofs and Arguments Pedo-Baptiſts produce for the baptizing of Infants. I ſhall only fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſire both Mr. <hi>Keach,</hi> and thoſe others whoſe Books I have now conſidered, ſeriouſly and impartially to weigh what I have ſaid in Anſwer to what they affirm concerning Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, its being only a Seal unto <hi>Abraham</hi> of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, and not ſo to any of his Seed, in my Infant-Baptiſm from Heaven, <hi>Pag.</hi> 228, unto 236. and ſhall only add my hearty Deſire our Opponents will truly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially weigh what hath been offered unto them, and determine, as they will anſwer it at the great Day of Accounts, which we all profeſs our ſelves Expectants of; and in caſe any of them will return any Anſwer to what I have written upon this Subject, I deſire they would do it with what ſpeed conveniently they may: My Age now tells me my appearing before our Lord Chriſt cannot be very far off, and I would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, either be convinced of my Error, ſuppoſe I have erred, (Infallibility I pretend not unto) which yet at preſent I am above any ſuſpicion that I have done, or may have opportunity to ſhew them the Inſufficiency of the Anſwers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by them.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 23. line 10. read <hi>ſome.</hi> P. 31. l. 10. after <hi>made,</hi> add <hi>muſt be fixed.</hi> P. 33. l. 19. read <hi>inſtitutes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
